Finding Aid for the Martin Thrope Papers LSC.2329
UCLA Library Special Collections
Martin Thrope papers
1968-2000, bulk 1969-1973
1969-1973
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.2329
.4 linear feet (1 document box)
From 1969 to 1974, Martin Thrope was a member of the of the team at Bolt Beranek and Newman (BBN), that implemented the ARPANET, the precursor to the Internet. His papers detail the BBN company of that time, and his work developing procedures for reports of network outages, installing Interface Message Processor (IMP) systems at various sites around the country, and designing specialized interfaces to connect a variety of host computers to the IMPs for connection to the ARPANET.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Selected items have been digitized for the KIHC Digital Collections: http://digital2.library.ucla.edu/internethistory/.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated by Martin Thrope to UCLA Kleinrock Internet History Center Donated by Martin Thrope in a deed of gift dated 31 Dec 2011.
Custodial History note
UCLA Kleinrock Internet History Center (KIHC) obtained the set of BBN materials directly from Martin Thrope. The files were donated to UCLA by Martin Thrope.
Former collection number and title
Originally acquired by Charlotte Brown, University Archivist for a proposed Kleinrock Center for Internet Studies at UCLA. Formerly KCIS 4; formerly titled Martin Thrope BNN papers
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942331793606533
Biographical/Historical note
From 1969 to 1974, after completing undergraduate studies at Harvard, Martin Thrope was a member of the team at Bolt Beranek & Newman (BBN) that implemented the Advanced Research Projects Agency Network (ARPANET) for the Advanced Research Projects Agency (ARPA) of the U.S. Department of Defense. The BBN team led by Frank Heart developed the Interface Message Processors (IMPs) which connected host systems to the ARPANET. Thrope connected host systems to the ARPANET, and made key contributions to the ARPANET architecture. Thrope developed a set of diagnostic procedures for producing specific information on line failures for reports of network outages of both IMPs and the phone lines that connected them, to be relayed to the phone company offices responsible for each line. BBN established a Network Control Center (NCC) run by Thrope which used a minicomputer, the NCC host, to analyze IMP status reports, print out alerts, and display the status of each IMP on a set of light panels mounted in wood grain box. For the NCC, Thrope compiled and maintained a comprehensive set of useful reference information on each IMP site and each phone line. In addition to his role in network operations, Thrope also designed and installed specialized interfaces sold by BBN to connect a variety of mainframe host computers to the IMPs at their sites. Toward the end of his time at BBN, he was a member of the team that designed a multiprocessor version of the IMP and its specialized hardware interfaces. After leaving BBN in 1974, Thrope earned his MBA degree from Harvard, followed by various management roles in organizations providing computer based products and services for the retail and financial industries.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of Martin Thrope, a member of the team at Bolt Beranek & Newman (BBN) that implemented the ARPANET, consisting of materials detailing his tenure at BBN from 1969 to 1974 and including: reports, brochures, correspondence, memorandum, manuals, photographs, slides, CDROM, and a VHS tape.
Arrangement note
The files within each series and subseries are arranged in chronological order. The series arrangement of the records is as follows:
Series 1: Correspondence, Documents, and Media from BBN
Series 2: Technical Memorandum and Problem Reports
Series 3: IMP manuals, 1971-1973
Computer science. Computer architecture and design -- Archives.; Computer networks -- United States -- Archives.; ARPANET (Computer network).; Internet -- History -- United States -- Archives.; Internet (Computer network) -- United States -- Archives.; Interface Message Processor.; United States. Advanced Research Projects Agency; Bolt, Beranek, and Newman; Heart, Frank; Thrope, Martin
- Series 1: Correspondence, Documents, and Media from BBN, 1968-2000
  Scope and Contents note
  Series 1 consists of BBN administrative documents and includes: correspondence, a personnel handbook, annual statements, a business plan, and a copy of personnel address list from 1971 and 1973. The series also includes: a videotape and brochure documenting BBN history, and photographs and slides of IMP equipment and BBN staff. The correspondence from Martin Thrope to Frank Heart in 1974 consists of Martin Thrope's plan to resign on 1974 September 6, and a list of responsibilities (HSMIMP documentation, host interface design, consultation services, and special host interfaces) to be passed on after the latter's resignation.
  - Photographs, 1968, 1972, 2000; 1 folders (Box 1, Folder 1)
    The series include photographs of BBN staff and a Univac 418 to IMP special host interface. There are six glossy finish black and white photographs of BBN staff members taken at BBN, Cambridge, Massachusetts in 1968. The BBN staff members were Frank Heart, Severo Ornstein, Dave Francis, Dave Katsuki, Ben Barket, Tony Michel, Mike Kraley, Dick Garber, Martin Thrope, Steve Jeske, Will Crowther, and Bob Bressler. There are 14 slides and a CDROM of images of the Univac 418 to IMP special host interface.
  - Correspondence and Memos, 1974-1975; 1 folders (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Administrative Documents, 1969, 1971, 1973; 1 folders (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - BBN History, 1976, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    This folder includes a brochure and VHS tape that documents BBN history and milestones in 1976 and 1994 respectively. The VHS tape titled "the History of the Future:Arpanet, Internet... and Beyond,Arpanet Celebration Dinner" was produced by BBN in 1994.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
    CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email AskLSC@library.ucla.edu.
- Series 2: Technical Memorandum and Problem Reports, 1972-1973
  Series 2 includes: a memorandum entitled "Guide to the Good stuff" providing a comprehensive set of useful reference information on each IMP site and each phone line, a memorandum detailing the NCC program used to display the status of each IMP on a set of light panels mounted in wood grain box, IMP downtime and line outage reports, and fixes to UCLA ready line notes.
  - Memorandum Guide to the Good Stuff, Apr 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - NCC program Memo, Feb 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Problem Reports, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series 3: Interface Message Processors (IMP) manuals, 1971-1973; 3 folders
  Series 3 includes: three manuals produced by BBN Computer Systems Division from 1971 and 1973. The manuals are: (Report No. 2061) dated January 1971 that describes the design, installation, and operation of a special interface that BBN built to connect the IMP to an IBM 360 computer; a manual dated 1973 April that describes the design, installation, and operation of a special interface that BBN built to connect the IMP to a Digital Equipment Corporation (DEC) PDP-10 host computer; and a manual that describes the design, installation, and operation of a special interface that BBN built to connect the IMP to a DEC PDP-15 host computer.
  Interface Message Processor.; Computer science. Computer architecture and design -- Archives.; Computer network resources.; Computer engineering -- Data processing.; ARPANET (Computer network).
  - Manual for the 360/IMP Special Interface, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Manual for the IMP-10 Special Interface, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Manual for the IMP-15 Special Interface, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)